Knowing ISIL's desire to destroy modern human lives, it's a natural extension for them to destroy cultural identity as well. Countless invading armies have done the same throughout history. We know that ISIL is profiting from the looting of sites, but we don't know the scale. This means that any object purchased on the market today from the Middle East could potentially be funding terrorism. When a site is looted, it's as if a puzzle already missing 90 percent of it pieces has had the rest obscured beyond recognition. This is ancient identity theft writ large. We know that there are two kinds of looting going on: looting by criminal elements like ISIL, and then more local looting by those that are desperate for money. We would all do the same to feed our families; I don't blame the local looters. I blame the middlemen, the unethical traffickers and an international art market that exploits often ambiguous or even completely nonexistent laws. We know looting is going on on a global scale and it's increasing, but presently we don't have any tools to stop it. This is beginning to change. My team and I have just completed a study looking at looting in Egypt. We looked at open-source data and mapped the entirety of looting across Egypt from 2002 to 2013. We found evidence of looting and site destruction at 267 sites, and mapped over 200,000 looting pits. It's astonishing. And putting that data together -- you can see the looting pits marked here. At one site, the looting got bad from 2009, 2011, 2012 -- hundreds and hundreds of pits. Putting all the data together, what we found is that, contrary to popular opinion, looting did not start to get worse in Egypt in 2011 after the Arab Spring, but in 2009, after the global recession. Thus, we've shown with big data that looting is fundamentally an economic issue. If we do nothing to stop the problem, all of Egypt's sites will be affected by looting by 2040. Thus, we are at a tipping point. We are the generation with all the tools and all the technologies to stop looting, but we're not working fast enough. Sometimes an archaeological site can surprise you with its resilience. I am just back from the field, where I co-led a joint mission with Egypt's Ministry of Antiquities at a site called Lisht. This site dates to the Middle Kingdom of Egypt between 2,000 and 1,750 BC. The Middle Kingdom was Ancient Egypt's Renaissance period. After a time of intense internal strife and environmental challenges, Egypt rebounded with an incredible resurgence of art, architecture and literature. It's a favorite period of time to study in Egypt, because it teaches us so much about how we can survive and thrive after great disasters. Now at this site, we had already mapped countless looting pits. Lisht is a royal site; there would have been thousands of people buried there who lived and worked at the court of Pharaoh. You can see this before and after; you see dozens of looting pits. North Lisht. This is in South Lisht, before and after. When we first visited the site, we could see the tombs of many high-ranking officials that had been looted. Let me put into perspective for you what was taken. Imagine a two meter by two meter area full of coffins, jewelry and incredible statuary. Multiply that times over a thousand. That's what was taken. So, when we started work, my Egyptian co-director, Mohamed Youssef, approached me and said, "We must work at this one particular tomb. It's been attacked by looters. If we don't do anything, they'll be back." Of course I agreed, but I didn't think we'd find anything. I thought the looters had stolen everything. What we started to find were the most incredible reliefs. Look at this painting -- it's just stunning. We started finding engraved inscriptions. And even the titles of the tomb owner -- he had titles like, "Overseer of the Army," "Overseer of the Treasury." I began to have hope. Maybe, just maybe we would find his name. For the ancient Egyptians, having their name last for eternity was their goal. And then one day, this appeared. This is the name of the tomb owner: Intef. You can see it written out here, in hieroglyphs. Working together with my Egyptian team, we had restored someone's name from 3,900 years ago. (Applause) Working together with my Egyptian colleagues, we celebrated this moment of shared discovery. What we were doing together was right and true. We found this incredible false door, mostly intact. On it we read about Intef and his inscriptions. You can actually even see him seated here. What I realized is that everything I had assumed about looted sites had been proven wrong. Every day on site we worked together with 70 Egyptians as colleagues and friends. In the face of so much hatred and ignorance against those in the Middle East, every moment on site felt like a protest for peace. When you work with those that don't look like you, or think like you, or speak like you, your shared mission of archaeological discovery erases all superficial differences. What I learned this season is that archaeology isn't about what you find. It's about what you can prove possible. Sometimes when you travel, you end up finding long-lost family -- not those with whom you share genes, but a shared entry in the book of life. This is Omer Farrouk, my brother. Omer's a Gufti from a village just North of Luxor, called Guft. Guftis are part of a celebrated tradition in Egyptology. They help with digging and work crew organization. Omer is my COO and CFO. I simply couldn't do work without him. One day many years ago, when I was a young graduate student and Omer was a young Gufti who couldn't speak much English, we learned, completely randomly, that we were born in the same year, the same month and the same day, six hours apart. Twins. (Laughter) Separated by an ocean, but forever connected for Ancient Egypt is our mother. I knew then we'd always work together -- not in my brain, but in the part of your soul that knows not everything can be explained. (Arabic) Omer by brother, I will always love you. (English) Omer my brother, I will always love you. So, just before my first dig in Egypt, my mentor, the very famous Egyptologist Professor William Kelly Simpson, called me into his office. He handed me a check for $2,000, and said, "This is to cover your expenses. Have a glorious adventure this summer. Someday you will do this for someone else." Thus, my TED Prize wish is partial payback, plus interest -- (Laughter) for a great human being's generosity and kindness. So, my wish. I wish for us to discover the millions of unknown archaeological sites around the world. By creating a 21st-century army of global explorers, we'll find and protect the world's hidden heritage, which contains clues to humankind's collective resilience and creativity. (Applause) Thank you. So how are we going to do this? We are going to build with the TED Prize money an online, crowdsource, citizen science platform to allow anyone in the world to engage with discovering archaeological sites. There are only a couple hundred of us space archaeologists around the world. It is my dream to engage the world with helping to find sites and protect them. What you'll do is sign in, create a username -- note that this particular username is already taken. (Laughter) You'll take a tutorial and you'll start work. I want to note at the outset that in no way will be sharing GPS data or mapping data for sites. We want to treat them like human patient data, and not reveal their locations. You'll then be dealt a card from a deck -- 20 x 20 meters or 30 x 30 meters, and you'll be looking for features. My team and I will have batch-processed large amounts of satellite data using algorithms in order for you to find things, so you'll be doing really good science. You'll then be starting to look. What do you see? Do you see a temple? Do you see a tomb? Do you see a pyramid? Do you see any potential site damage or site looting? You'll then begin to mark what's there. And off to the side are always going to be rich examples of exactly what you're seeing, to help guide you. All the data that you help us collect will be shared with vetted authorities, and will help create a new global alarm system to help protect sites. But it's not just going to stop there. All the archaeologists with whom we share your discoveries will take you with them as they begin to excavate them, by using Periscope, Google Plus and social media. A hundred years ago, archaeology was for the rich. Fifty years ago, it was for men. Now it's primarily for academics. Our goal is to democratize the process of archaeological discovery, and allow anyone to participate. Ninety-four years ago, Howard Carter discovered the tomb of King Tut. Who is the next Howard Carter? It might be you. By creating this platform, we will find the millions of places occupied by the billions of people that came before us. If we want to answer the big questions about who we are and where we've come from, the answers to those questions do not lie in pyramids or palaces, but in the cities and villages of those that came before us. If we want to learn about the past, it's time we inverted the pyramids. Acknowledging that the past is worth saving means so much more. It means that we're worth saving, too. And the greatest story ever told is the story of our shared human journey. But the only way we're going to be able to write it is if we do it together. Come with me. Thank you. (Applause)
En connaissant le désir de Daech de détruire des vies humaines, détruire l'identité culturelle en est une extension naturelle. Dans l'histoire, d'innombrables armées d'envahisseurs l'ont fait. Nous savons que Daech profite du pillage des sites mais ignorons à quel point. Cela signifie que tout objet acheté aujourd'hui sur le marché et venant du Moyen-Orient pourrait financer le terrorisme. Quand un site est pillé, c'est comme si, pour un puzzle dont il manque 90% des pièces, on l’obscurcissait pour le rendre impossible à distinguer. C'est un important vol d'ancienne identité. Nous savons qu'il se produit deux types de pillages : le pillage fait par des criminels tels que Daech et un pillage plus local fait par ceux ayant besoin d'argent. Nous ferions tous la même chose pour nourrir notre famille ; je ne reproche rien aux pilleurs locaux. J'en veux aux intermédiaires, les trafiquants non éthiques et un marché d'art international qui exploitent des lois souvent ambiguës voire complètement inexistantes. Nous savons qu'il y a de plus en plus de pillage à l'échelle mondiale mais, actuellement, nous n'avons aucun outil pour l'arrêter. Cela commence à changer. Mon équipe et moi venons de finir une étude sur le pillage en Égypte. Nous avons considéré les données open source et avons cartographié tous les pillages en Égypte de 2002 à 2013. Nous avons des preuves de pillage et de destruction dans 267 sites et avons cartographié plus de 200 000 lieux de pillages. C'est stupéfiant. En réunissant les données -- les lieux sont représentés ici. Sur un site, le pillage augmente tous les ans : 2009, 2011, 2012 -- des lieux par centaines. En réunissant les données, nous avons découvert que, contrairement à l'idée populaire, le pillage n'a pas augmenté en Égypte en 2011 après le Printemps arabe, mais en 2009, après la récession mondiale. Ainsi avec le big data, nous avons montré que le pillage est principalement un problème économique. Si nous ne réglons pas le problème, tous les sites d’Égypte seront affectés par le pillage d'ici 2040. Nous sommes donc à un moment déterminant. Nous sommes la génération ayant les outils et les technologies pour arrêter le pillage mais nous ne travaillons pas assez vite. Parfois, un site archéologique peut surprendre par sa résilience. J'étais sur le terrain, j'ai codirigé une mission commune avec le ministère égyptien des antiquités sur un site appelé Lisht. Le site date du Moyen Empire égyptien entre 2 000 et 1 750 ans avant JC. Cela fait partie de la Renaissance de l’Égypte antique. Après une période d'intenses conflits internes et de défis environnementaux, l’Égypte s'est réunifiée avec un renouveau incroyable en art, architecture et littérature. C'est une des meilleures périodes à étudier en Égypte car elle nous en apprend beaucoup sur comment survivre et prospérer après des catastrophes. Sur ce site, nous avions cartographié d'innombrables lieux de pillage. Lisht est un site royal ; des milliers de personnes y ont été enterrées après vécu et travaillé à la cour du Pharaon. Vous voyez l'avant-après ; il y a des douzaines de lieux de pillage. Le nord de Lisht. Voici le sud de Lisht, avant et après. Lors de notre première visite, nous voyions les tombeaux d'officiels hauts placés qui avaient été pillés. Laissez-moi remplacer cela dans son contexte. Imaginez une zone de deux mètres sur deux pleine de cercueils, de bijoux et d'incroyables statues. Multipliez cela par mille. C'est ce qui a été pris. Au début de notre travail, mon codirecteur égyptien, Mohamed Youssef, est venu me dire : « Nous devons travailler sur ce tombeau. Il a été attaqué par des pilleurs. Si nous ne faisons rien, ils reviendront. » J'étais d'accord mais ne croyais pas que nous trouverions quelque chose. Je pensais que les pilleurs avaient tout volé. Nous avons commencé à trouver des restes incroyables. Regardez cette peinture, magnifique. Nous avons trouvé des inscriptions gravées. Et les titres du propriétaire du tombeau, des titres comme « Gardien de l'Armée », « Gardien de la Trésorerie ». J'ai commencé à espérer. Peut-être trouverions-nous son nom. Pour les Égyptiens, que leur nom perdure l'éternité était le but. Puis un jour, ceci est apparu. C'est le nom du propriétaire du tombeau : Intef. Vous le voyez écrit en hiéroglyphes. En travaillant avec mon équipe égyptienne, nous avons rétabli le nom de quelqu'un vivant il y a 3 900 ans. (Applaudissements) En travaillant avec mes collègues égyptiens, nous avons fêté ce moment de découverte commune. Ce que nous faisions ensemble était bien et vrai. Nous avons découvert cette fausse porte, intacte. Dessus, nous avons lu l'histoire d'Intef et ses inscriptions. Vous pouvez le voir assis ici. J'ai réalisé que tout ce que je supposais des sites pillés était faux. Chaque jour, sur le site, nous travaillions avec 70 Égyptiens en tant que collègues et amis. Face à tant de haine et d'ignorance envers ceux du Moyen-Orient, à chaque instant passé sur le site, nous réclamions la paix. En travaillant avec des gens qui ne vous aiment pas, ne pensent pas ou ne parlent pas comme vous, votre mission commune de découverte archéologique efface toute différence superficielle. Ce que j'ai appris, c'est qu'en archéologie, il ne s'agit pas de la découverte mais de ce que nous pouvons prouver être possible. Parfois en voyageant, vous trouvez de la famille perdue depuis longtemps -- vous ne partagez pas de gènes mais une entrée commune dans le livre de la vie. Voici Omer Farrouk, mon frère. Omer est un Gufti d'un village juste au nord de Louxor, appelé Guft. Les Guftis font partie d'une tradition célébrée en Égypte. Ils aident aux fouilles et au management d'équipe. Il est mon chef d'exploitation et directeur financier. Je ne pourrais pas travailler sans lui. Un jour il y a plusieurs années, quand j'étais étudiante et qu'Omer était un jeune Gufti ne parlant pas bien anglais, nous avons appris par hasard que nous étions nés la même année, le même mois et le même jour à six heures d'écart. Des jumeaux. (Rires) Séparés par un océan mais pour toujours liés car l’Égypte ancienne est notre mère. Nous travaillerons toujours ensemble -- cela ne venait pas du cerveau mais de la partie de mon âme qui sait que tout ne peut pas être expliqué. (Arabe) Omer, mon frère, je t'aimerai toujours. (Anglais) Omer, mon frère, je t'aimerai toujours. Juste avant ma première fouille en Égypte, mon mentor, l'égyptologue très connu, le professeur William Kelley Simpson m'a demandé de venir le voir. Il m'a tendu un chèque de 2 000$ et a dit : « C'est pour couvrir tes dépenses. Que ton aventure soit illustre cet été. Un jour, tu feras ceci pour quelqu'un d'autre. » Recevoir le TED Prize serait en partie pour le rembourser, avec intérêts -- (Rires) pour la générosité et la gentillesse d'un être humain merveilleux. Mon vœu. Je souhaite que nous découvrions les millions de sites archéologiques inconnus à travers le monde. En créant au XXIe siècle une armée d'explorateurs mondiaux, nous trouverons et protégerons l'héritage caché du monde qui détient des indices sur la résilience et la créativité collectives humaines. (Applaudissements) Merci. Comment allons-nous faire ? Avec l'argent du TED Prize, nous allons mettre en place une plateforme collaborative en ligne de sciences citoyennes pour permettre à quiconque dans le monde de prendre part à la découverte de sites archéologiques. Nous ne sommes que quelques centaines d'archéologues spatiaux dans le monde. Mon rêve est d'intéresser le monde à nous aider à trouver des sites et à les protéger. Vous vous inscrirez, créez un nom d'utilisateur -- notez que celui-ci en particulier est déjà pris. (Rires) Vous suivrez un tutoriel et vous travaillerez. Je veux dire dès le début que nous ne partagerons pas les données GPS ou de cartographie des sites. Ce sera comme les données d'un patient humain, nous ne révélerons pas leur localisation. Ensuite vous recevrez une carte de 20 x 20 mètres ou 30 x 30 mètres et vous chercherez des caractéristiques. Mon équipe et moi avons traité un gros volume de données satellites avec des algorithmes afin que vous trouviez des choses et fassiez de la bonne science. Ensuite vous regarderez. Que voyez-vous ? Voyez-vous un temple ? Voyez-vous un tombeau ? Voyez-vous une pyramide ? Voyez-vous de potentiels dégâts ou du pillage sur un site ? Puis vous marquerez ce qu'il y a. Et sur le côté, il y aura toujours des exemples riches de ce que vous voyez exactement, pour vous guider. Toutes les données que vous nous aidez à collecter seront partagées avec les autorités habilitées et aideront à créer un nouveau système mondial d'alarme pour aider à protéger les sites. Mais cela ne s'arrêtera pas là. Tous les archéologues avec qui nous partageons vos découvertes vous amèneront avec eux lors de l’excavation en utilisant Periscope, Google Plus et les médias sociaux. Il y a cent ans, l'archéologie était pour les riches. Il y a 50 ans, c'était pour les hommes. Aujourd'hui, c'est surtout pour les chercheurs. Notre but est de démocratiser le processus de découverte archéologique et de permettre à tout le monde de participer. Il y a 94 ans, Howard Carter a découvert le tombeau de Toutankhamon. Qui sera le prochain Howard Carter ? Peut-être vous. En créant cette plateforme, nous trouverons des millions d'endroits occupés par des milliards de personnes qui nous ont précédés. Si nous voulons répondre aux grandes questions sur notre identité et d'où nous venons, les réponses à ces questions ne sont pas dans les pyramides ou palaces mais dans les villes et villages de ceux qui nous ont précédés. Si nous voulons en savoir plus sur le passé, il est temps d'inverser les pyramides. Reconnaître que le passé mérite d'être préservé est bien plus significatif. Cela veut dire que nous méritons, aussi, d'être sauvés. Et la meilleure histoire jamais racontée est l'histoire de notre voyage commun en tant qu'humains. Mais nous ne pouvons l'écrire qu'ensemble. Venez avec moi. Merci. (Applaudissements)